Alright then friends, in this video we're going to talk about constructors and
constructors again play a center role in in almost every day that you write
code and Java and we're important that you have a good understanding of this
concept as well. So first things first what are constructors and what is the
specialty about them right? So constructors are methods right that's the
first thing to understand about them but they're special methods right and
what is that specialty? The specialty lies in these constructors they're called
implicitly automatically at the time and whenever we create an object of the
class. That means we do not need to call them explicitly ourselves. We don't do
that we can't do that right there. Always automatically implicitly called at
the time and whenever we create an object of the class and that's unlike how you
call methods right how methods are called because a method is only called once
you place a call to it. Without that it will never be executed but a
constructor body is executed every time you create an object of that class. That's
their specialty right? That means the code that you would need to be executed or
initialized at first you might want to put that inside a constructor of a class. Some
of the code that you would want to run anytime an object is created and you
would not to be now you would not want that to be called automatically put that
code inside the constraint of body. Let's go on and have a look at that with
real-world analogy. So what I'll do is I'll go to arm.war.org or opt.work for that
for that matter and I'll just say a new class and this time I'll say day with
constrictors because that's what we are going to do. We're going to try a
hands-on with constrictors in Java. All right so we'll have the customary
main maker and let's again go back and use a user code that is or user
example of the classic example of humans right and this would make exact or
this would make complete sense but before we do that let me just go on and tell
you about the things I told you what a constructors and what is the specialty
about them but which functions or which methods are called constructive what is
the representation of a constructor because I told you it's a method first so
which methods are not considered ordinary but constructive methods. The first
property there are a couple of properties the first property is that is
constructors have the same name as the class name. That is the name of the class
and the name of the constructor method is the same. The second property is that
is constructors in Java do not have a return type not even white right otherwise
it would be an ordinary simple method so they do not have a return type not
even white. So to just give an example if we're I walk you through a real
technology of humans I'll just define a constructor so I told you the name of the
class has to be the same as the name of the of the constructor. So here you're
seeing play with constructors is the same name as the class name that's the
first point more constructors and the second thing if you've observed is I've
not put in a return time because constructors do not have a return type not
even white. This is a constructor now and just to give you a proof of that I'll
just say a sound and I'll say constructor court right and inside me I'm just
going to create a new object of this class and if you get this printed out on
screen you know this is called in a spatial situation that is I did not call
this automatically explicitly sorry but it was called automatically right I'm
sorry let's go on and run this and you're seeing construct to call it and that
was automatically because you just created an object you did not call it
explicitly and it was called right and why is it called because now if you zoom
into this line we were saying new play with constructors we know this creates an
object of a class in Java but if you zoom into this these circular braces and
these ones they're the same that means it is not so implicit but just that you
just go on and do your job you know worry about the constructor call because
it's been taken here at the object creation time and no matter how many
objects you create let's say I create two objects of this class it would be
called that many times let's run this again we'll get it twice let's try to
all but if there was a normal method in this in this class let's say white
fun it will say sound and I'll say fun called this will not be called unless you
call it say we just get consider call construct a call but not fun called if
you do not call it explicitly for example let's just do that I'll say now you
say I'll say inside constructor or consider call and then fun call let's run
this and that is what you saw so for this to be called it has to be a call
but for constructors to be called you don't need to worry about that you need
to worry about calling them that's how constructors work right so we have the
same name as the class name and and they are called automatically at the time
and whenever you create an object of that class right now obviously we're done
with this I'll just come in this out and walk you through what is the what is
the real-world analogy when does it make sense and I'll just walk you
through where we would be stuck with the problem and then constructors would
come to the rescue that's how we learn the better way right so what I'll do is
I'll go on and create a new class I'll call it class human right but it says
that human is already found in this package it cannot be a duplicate class so
we have two options either we put it in that other package org.work for it to
be worked one we just deal with something else for now let's just call it for
example we can call it class let's say student all right okay so let's let's
think about a scenario where we have to register some students right and the
requirement from the client comes in that is at the time the student comes on
the very first day we have to at least save a couple of their details that is
their name and their uniquely right other details like the gender which plays
they come from that can be saved later on but we want the system to be able to
save two details at the time the student comes to the college from the
very first day they're very explicit with their requirement they want this
these particular two details to be saved mandatory early on that day but rest of
the details can be saved later on so we as a development team think about it
and and come to the conclusion this is a classic case a classic example a
classic situation to use constructors right I'll tell you why so I'll say
a student but now this is a constructor obviously you know because the name of
the method and the name of the class is the same right this makes it a
constructor so whenever I create a student object right this constructor would
be called let's try doing that with the main let's say student first to
new student and it would be called that's fine but it doesn't serve the purpose
because the requirement from the client was at the time the student comes in I
want the system to be able to save two details mandatory that is the name and
the ID but this doesn't save it anywhere so we as a development team what
about it and came to this particular code that is I'll just say in ID and I'll
say string new more on strings in detail in the next or in later video but if
no strings are just what what you'll find in other languages let us you want to
store a bunch of characters together you have the string type in Java with a
capital S because it's an in-built class all right so ID and name and now I want
these two to be stored at the time the object is created of that student
right so for that what I'll do is see and this is a requirement driven programming
as I always say programming is requirement driven not just depends on my mood
right so this time what I'll do ahead is just like you can have parameterized
methods you can have parameterized constructor as well so I'll do is I'll say
student and I'll say integer ID and I'll say string name and then you'll say
now and then why did I have parameters because I want this to be working as
permit lines three requirement and that was at the time the object was created
the system needs to take two details and I know at the time the student object
is created the constructor would be called and at that time it needs to take two
details at that very time from the object right and these two details would come
in from somewhere else where you create an object and I would need to pass these
to these so I've created them as local variables these are instance variables
right so I would need to before it reaches this body because I would know the
local variables would be dead that's their lifespan but as I told you in the
previous video that is when we talked about instance variables instance
variables live as long as the object is alive so I know they would live much
longer than these right so I would need to pass the details of this ID and name
to this ID and name and how can I do that you will see this kind of first
syntax almost every day in job and that is if I say ID equal to ID now which
ID am I referring to first of all let's see if this is an error this ID and
this ID can they exist the same name yes they can why because these are
instance variables these are local variables they are at two different levels and I
can have two variables at two different scopes with the same name and that's
perfectly fun and for better readability in fact they prefer them calling the
same now you want to save this ID to this ID if you say ID equal ID this is just
the local variable because at the local level the local variables take
precedence right but that is the second usage of the key word this to overcome
this is called shadowing why because the local variable is set to be shadowing
the instance variable and here I need to overcome shadowing and in in times
where I need to overcome shadowing that is where the this key word makes a
comeback and that is I can say this to ID to ID that means this to ID refers to
the instance variable and ID refers to the local variable because shadowing
right here I have overcome shadowing and similarly I'll say this name to name you'll
say as I said you'll find this kind of syntax almost every day right so just
get used to it just try to understand what I'm doing here that is I'm just
mapping the variable values that is the variables at the local level to the
variables at the instance level this is how we do it and at this line nine
number 26 ID and name would be dead but these ones would remain because I had
mapped them thanks to the currently executing object that magical
way of referring to the currently executing object and this is both my
requirement now how do you call it this is an error now that is no longer true
no longer correct that is you cannot create objects in Java like this now
because it says arguments and parameters don't match because this constructor
call it takes two parameters I would have to pass to arguments right and
what I'll do is as always we'll take it through scanner and say scanner
new scanner and I'll say us out enter ID and name of the new student
I'll do is I'll say int file you're in local variable of mean does not conflict
with those variables right different scope so it works so I'll say scan dot
next int and I told you if you have to take a string after an integer right
do a empty next line because it takes that slashing and then I'll say string
name equal to scan dot next line right and then pass these to the constructor
call ID and the error goes away so at the time now you're creating an object
in Java like this and the syntax is perfectly valid correct syntax right
because you're passing arguments with that call so this and this does it
look the same yes it does that ID and name the local variable of variables of
mean the values of those are passed into the local variables of the
constructor and the local variables values of the constraints passed to the
instance variables right so that is my requirement just works and then
afterwards whenever you want to print those out there are different ways to do
that the first way is not to the recommended way I'll tell you in a later
video when we are talking about Java beans right but for now let's say
there is an audit or you won't access their names all you have to do is just say
set for example student emails and you will see first dot name and I'll
concatenate it with first dot ID see let's just go on and run this it
relaxes the instant variables what does it say no suitable constraint account for
scanner why because we missed system yeah see again the arguments and
parameters didn't match because the now you know why does this works in now
try to interlate things in your mind that's the beauty of it when you
understand concept you know what is going on behind the scenes in the language
as well or what is going on in someone else code as well see now why does this
fail is why did it say no suitable constraint account for scanner why because
the scanner class behind the scenes takes one argument and we did not pass
that right so they don't match so that's why we say system dot in pass it to
what it takes the error should be got right let's run this says and try the name
of the new student as a 345 and I'll say for example let's just put it to
snare still till snare and I need to win it later on obviously we'll have a
menu driven program that would it would take more than one student details that
would be a complete program here we're shortly reaching that point as with
right and but for now this was my requirement at the very first place because if
you do not pass the idea and the name of the new student object it won't work
it won't move forward your program right it has to be mandatory the other
details the system said they could be taken later on like for example string
location or string skills but we wanted these to be taken at the very first
instance these we could take with different methods as well right and but
you might be wondering until now we were not dealing with constructors but
we are written a lot of code here see how many files we've written until now
all right so I did not discuss constructors but I'll tell you that inside every
class in Java there is a by default constructor it's called the default
constructor nor surprisingly right it has the same name as of the class name
doesn't have a return type right and if you don't write your own
constructor every class as its own every class has its default constructor but
the moment you start to write your own constructor there is no such thing
called a default constructor now right and why didn't it give us an error
until then until now because we went writing around customers now you know
why did this line always work without obviously arguments because there was
that default constructor always because now you know that constructors are
called automatically at the time and whenever we create an object to the class
and we have been creating objects all through these lectures and videos but
we never wrote a constructor why did that still work because in those cases the
default constructor was called right now the next point I'm going to make here is
now they say some students do not want to put in their names and IDs at the
very first date they've just come come for counseling and they are still not
sure whether they join the college so the system now should allow for certain
rare cases where the student doesn't want to save their or give their details
like you name an idea at the very first day after thinking about it whether they
want to join the college or not they would want to but not at the very first
instance but some of the students the details should be saved right so the
system should allow that and for that very reason now we as a development team
think about it and again not just because we are in the mood to do that
because the requirement tells us to it and it forces us to do that and in the
same way you can overload methods you can overload constructor as well so I'll do
it for that kind of a situation this is a very good program now right a
beautiful program because it demonstrates everything as if when we are stuck
and then we will get a solution and we say this time our constructor without
parameters it doesn't do anything why because id and name would they have
default values yes they won't why because again they defined at the
instance level at height I told you instance variables have default value in
Java id will have zero name because it's a reference variable it would have
null so if some of the students don't want to put in their details now this
will also work see let's say second new student without arguments now works
because we have put in a constructor which is parameterless we have overloaded
constructors and when you pass to this one would be called when you pass new
arguments this one would be called this is a great example of understanding
constructors from a real world perspective and why would use it as I said
almost every single day in Java programming in your careers right so just
think about it take care it over that after the video is done just try to
manipulate it just take your own example minus a student your might be a
teacher you might be a furniture class you might be a shared class you might be
a table class you might be a smartphone class just think about it come up your
own examples write your own and just try to interlate things then right and
I'll see you in the next video